A Guide to the Papers of Breece D'J Pancake, 1961-1990
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Breece D'J Pancake, 1961-1990
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
10975
This collection contains 315 items in 2 Hollinger boxes, ca. one linear foot.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The papers of Breece D'J Pancake were loaned to the Library by John Casey of Charlottesville, Virginia, on August 22, 1990.
Biographical/Historical Information
Pancake was born Breece Dexter Pancake on June 29, 1952, to Clarence Robert and Helen Frazier Pancake and grew up along Route 60 in Cabell County, West Virginia. He graduated from Marshall University, Huntington, West Virginia, in June of 1974, and lacked only his language requirement to complete his M.A. at the University of Virginia at the time of his death. While at the University of Virginia, he was a graduate assistant teaching creative writing on the Emily Clark Balch and Henry Hoyns Fellowships. He also served on the staff of the Virginia Quarterly Review, and had been awarded the Jefferson Cup by the Jefferson Society. Pancake had previously taught at the Fork Union and Staunton Military Academies.
His literary career began in 1975 when he was paid a flat fee to write feature stories for The Cabell Record, usually about people in the Cabell County vicinity. By 1977, he had two short fiction stories accepted for publication by the Atlantic Monthly Magazine. His book of short stories was published posthumously through the efforts of his literary executor, John Casey, and his mother, Helen Pancake, a librarian at the Milton Public Library.
For additional biographical information please see the article on Pancake in Comtemporary Authors Volume 123, pp. 292-294 (copy in control folder).
Scope and Content Information
The papers of Breece Pancake (1952-1979) a short story writer from Milton, West Virginia, 315 items (2 Hollinger boxes, ca. one linear foot), 1961-1990, consists mainly of material related to John Casey's activities as his literary executor. Included in this material is correspondence of Casey and Helen Pancake, much of it from Pancake's mother to Casey; seven letters or notes from Breece Pancake; typescripts, setting copy, and galley proofs of The Stories of Breece D'J Pancake; and material related to the attempts of Mark Rance, a documentary filmmaker with Appalachian roots, to secure funding and to produce a script for a movie, radio play, and a theatrical play, all based on Pancake's work. Rance calls the screenplay by various titles, "Ridge Runners," "Hollow," and "The Honored Dead." The screenplay is set in Pancake's imaginary mountain town of Rock Camp and uses characters from several different stories of Pancake.
Other material includes royalty statements, printed reviews of The Stories of Breece D'J Pancake, photographs of Breece Pancake and his family, John Casey's "Afterword" for The Stories of Breece D'J Pancake with author's corrections, "The Hills of Home," a review of The Stories of Breece D'J Pancake by Raymond Nelson, and "Breece D'J Pancake" by Cynthia Kadohata.
The correspondence is chiefly that of Pancake's mother, Helen Pancake, and John Casey concerning the work of Breece Pancake, the publication of the collection of his stories, and the production of a screenplay based on Pancake's writing. Some of the correspondents and topics of this correspondence include: Casey's attempts to secure financial aid for Pancake (1976 May 18); The New Yorker editor, Daniel Menaker, concerning "The Honored Dead" (1979 Apr 18); the publication of John Casey's book Testimony and Demeanor(1979 May 1); Pancake playing the harmonica (1982 Jan 22); Lee Goerner (1982 Jan 31); discussion concerning the dedication for Stories of Breece D'J Pancake(1982 Apr 13); Jayne Anne Phillips (EC 1982 May 5); James Boatwright (1982 May 18); Ronald Sharp, Kenyon Review editor (1982 Jun 1); Andre Dubus (EC 1982 Oct 10); a letter about Pancake's book from editor Peter Davison to Barbara Bannon of Publisher's Weekly(1982 Oct 22); John Casey to Joyce Carol Oates concerning the publication of a Pancake story in The Ontario Review(1983 Jan 6); Alan Cheuse (PC 1983 Mar 5); biographical information about Pancake (1983 Jun 22); family background (1983 Jul 7); Carlos [Santos ?] (1985 Jan 21 & n.d.); Helen Pancake's move to Florida (1985 Aug 1); Mike [Jennings ?] and his concern over Pancake as a "cult figure" (1989 Mar 9 & 16 and Apr 2 & 5); and Cynthia [Kadohata ?] and her article about Pancake (1989 Apr 12).
A large portion of the correspondence consists of letters concerning the motion picture and television rights and the production of the screenplay based on Pancake's stories (1983 Mar 17, 22, 24 and Apr 1, 7; 1984 Apr 30 and May 8; 1985 Jan 30, Mar 29, Apr 9, and Nov 18; 1986 Jan 16, 23 and Feb 12; 1987 Jan 13; 1989 Jan 10 and Mar 29; 1990 Apr 20; and n.y. Jan 7).
The correspondence of Breece D'J Pancake includes the following correspondents or subjects: Robie Macauley concerning "The Mark" (1976 May 25); efforts to get Peter Taylor or John Casey for a spring workshop at Randolph-Macon Woman's College (1978 Sep 18); and an offer by Pancake to do an article on "yellow slavery" for the Atlantic Monthly(1979 Jan 21); Pancake's last letter to John Casey (1979 Mar 25); and Richard Jones (1979 Apr 12).
Contents List
- Correspondence & Miscellaneous
  - Correspondence of Helen Pancake and John Casey 1976-1990, n.d., 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Correspondence of Breece D'J Pancake 1976-1979, 7 items (Box 1)
  - Photographs of Breece D'J Pancake and Family 1961, 1971, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Reviews of The Stories of Breece D'J Pancake1980-1990, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Royalty Statements for The Stories of Breece D'J Pancake 1984-1989 (Box 1)
- Manuscripts
  - Manuscripts by or about Breece Pancake
    - "Breece D'J Pancake" by Cynthia Kadohata 1989 ? (Box 1)
    - "Hills of Home" by Raymond Nelson - A Review of The Stories of Breece D'J Pancake1984 & n.d. (Box 1)
    - The Stories of Breece D'J Pancake, Incomplete pages of manuscript and typescript (Box 1)
    - The Stories of Breece D'J Pancake 1983, Setting Copy (Box 2)
    - The Stories of Breece D'J Pancake ca. 1983 (Box 2)
      "Afterword" by John Casey with author's corrections
    - Galley Proof of The Stories of Breece D'J Pancake1983, Marked Set (Box 2)
  - Adaptations of The Stories of Breece D'J Pancake
    - Hollow The Stories of Breece D'J Pancake 1986 (Box 2)
      Screenplay adaptation by Mark Rance (First Draft), with a letter from Rance to John Casey.
    - Hollow The Stories of Breece D'J Pancake 1986 (Box 2)
      Screenplay adaption by Mark Rance
    - The Honored Dead The Stories of Breece D'J Pancake 1987 (Box 2)
      Application for a grant to produce the screenplay
    - Ridge Runners The Stories of Breece D'J Pancake (Box 2)
      Motion picture story outline
    - The Stories of Breece D'J Pancake 1985 ? (Box 2)
      Application for a grant from the Humanities Foundation of West Virginia to plan and script the film
    - Two programs for Radio based on The Stories of Breece D'J Pancake by Mark Rance 1987 (Box 2)